<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="webtools">
	<title>Projects</title>
	<para>
		The most popular of the projects we deal with are the J2EE ones, such as Dynamic Web Project, EJB Project, or EAR project. <productname>JBoss Tools</productname> web projects include Struts, JSF and Seam projects. These are referred to as faceted projects. This chapter will cover facets, which are used to provide a consistent structure and packaging features to any type of project.
	</para>
	
	<section>
		<title>Faceted Projects Overview</title>
		<para>
			The idea behind faceted projects is that each project can accept units of functionality, or facets, which can be added or removed by the user. These facets either add to the project's classpath, enable a builder, or watch the project in some other fashion. Typically every project concerned has at least one facet when it is created. As an example, a Web project has a WebDoclet facet, or an EJB Project has an EJB Module facet as prerequisites.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			WTP projects have been criticized for being over-engineered or too restrictive in their design. WTP projects are set up in a tree-relationship to each other, where one project can be a child of another. For example, an EAR project may have a Web Project child, an EJB project child, or other types.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			However, the benefit of this is that the structure of your projects is then known and packaging it up <emphasis>should</emphasis> be trivial. If your project is non-standard, or you feel too confined by such rigid structural requirements, you can still choose to package your project using the Archives plugin (see <xref linkend="Project_archivesView"/>).
		</para>
	</section>

	
	<section>
		<title>Adding Facets to a Project</title>
		
		<para>
			This section will cover the facets added by <property>JBoss Tools</property> and show how you can configure them in a project by adding new ones or modifying existing facet configurations.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			One way to configure the facets is doing it while organizing a new project. To demonstrate this let&apos;s create a new <guilabel>Dynamic Web Project</guilabel> by selecting <menuchoice><guimenuitem>File</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>New</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Other...</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Web</guimenuitem><guimenuitem>Dynamic Web Project</guimenuitem></menuchoice>.
		</para>
		<figure>
			<title>New Dynamic Web Project</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/webtools/webtools_1.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>Click the <guibutton>Next</guibutton> button and you will see a Dynamic Web Project page like on the figure below.</para>
		
		<para>
			The first page of most WTP projects allows you to target a specific runtime, which represents a server's library location. It will also provide you the ability to add this project to an EAR project and select a preselected default set of facets, called a configuration, rather than manually select each required facet.
		</para>
		<para>
			Selecting the runtime allows the project to install the proper classpaths to the project so it knows what code to compile against.
		</para>
		
		<figure id="dyn_web_project">
			<title>New Dynamic Web Project</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/webtools/webtools_2.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>
			Click the <guibutton>Modify</guibutton> button next to the <guilabel>Configuration</guilabel> section to open a wizard which allows you to modify the chosen configuration. The wizard is shown in the image below.
		</para>
		
		<figure id="project_facets">
			<title>Project Facets Wizard</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/webtools/webtools_3.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		
		<para>Here part of the listed facets are those which are provided by WTP. Some of them are added by <property>JBoss Tools</property>. They are:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>BIRT Charting Runtime Component</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>BIRT Reporting Runtime Component</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>JBoss ESB</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>JBoss Portlets</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>JBoss Web Services</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Seam</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>
		
		<para>
			On this wizard page you can enable or disable any facet as well as change its version. What you should note here is that some facets or facets versions may conflict with each other. In case of incompatibility you will be notified in the combo box underneath.
		</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Facet Constraints</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/webtools/webtools_4.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>When switching on the <guilabel>Runtimes</guilabel> tab on the right you will see the current server Runtime.</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Runtimes on the Project Facets Wizard</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/webtools/webtools_5.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>
			On this tab you can also create a new Server Runtime and make it primary by enabling it and then clicking the <guibutton>Make Primary</guibutton> button.
		</para>
		
		<para>
			Clicking on the <guibutton>OK</guibutton> button will save the chosen configuration of the facets and return you to the Dynamic Web Project wizard (see <xref linkend="dyn_web_project"/>). Additional pages in the wizard are specific to either the project type or the facets selected.
		</para>

		
		<para>
			If you need to configure the facets for an existing project, right click on the project, select <guimenuitem>Properties</guimenuitem> and then select <guilabel>Project Facets</guilabel>. This will bring up the Project Facets wizard (see <xref linkend="project_facets"/>), where you can create your own custom facets configuration.
		</para>
		
		<para/>
	
	</section>
	<section id="rel_resources_links">
		<title>Relevant Resources Links</title>
		
		<para>
			More information on the WTP facets can be found in the <ulink url="http://help.eclipse.org/ganymede/index.jsp?topic=/org.eclipse.jst.j2ee.doc.user/topics/cfacets.html">Eclipse help</ulink>.
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
