<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<chapter id="extensions" xreflabel="extensions">
   <?dbhtml filename="extensions"?>
   <title>Extension API</title>
   <para>This chapter will outline how to contribute your own Server type with some default
      behavior.</para>

   <section>
      <title>Why??</title>

      <para>You might be asking yourself why you&apos;d need to extend this framework if JMX is
         a standard. Perhaps you want a connection to be automatically created after some specific
         action, or perhaps you want your connection wizard to do more than simply set a host and
         port. JBoss, for example, requires setting some credentials on the client machine, but
         using JBoss classes to do it. This requires that the connection have access to JBoss
         jars.</para>
   </section>

   <section>
      <title>Core Extensions</title>

      <para>To create your own JMX Connection type, you must use the
         org.jboss.tools.jmx.core.MBeanServerConnectionProvider extension point. This point takes
         one child, a connectionProvider with a class that implements
         org.jboss.tools.jmx.core.IConnectionProvider.</para>
      
      <para>An IConnectionProvider is responsible for creation and deletion of IConnectionWrapper
         objects. It must also keep a list of listeners that it is expected to inform when a
         connection is added or removed from its list. </para>
      
      <para>Each IConnectionWrapper is expected to handle running arbitrary JMX runnables or getting
         a "Root" object representing all JMX nodes. There are some utility methods the
         IConnectionWrapper can make use of.</para>
   </section>


   <section>
      <title>UI Extensions</title>
      <para>There are two extension points currently approved for use in the UI</para>
      <itemizedlist>
         <listitem>
            <para>org.jboss.tools.jmx.ui.providerUI - provide an icon, id, displayable name, and
               wizardPage class for creation of new connections</para>
         </listitem>
         <listitem>
            <para>org.jboss.tools.jmx.ui.attribute.controls - allows you to map class types to some
            Control to present them in the MBean Editor</para>
            <para>We hope, this guide helped you to get started with the JBoss JMX Tools. Besides, for additional information you are welcome on <ulink
               url="http://www.jboss.com/index.html?module=bb&amp;op=viewforum&amp;f=201">JBoss forum</ulink>.</para>
         </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
   </section>

</chapter>
