<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<chapter id="how_to"  xreflabel="how_to">
    <?dbhtml filename="how_to.html"?>
    <title>How to ...</title>
    <para>This chapter will give you answers on most popular questions asked by JMX plugin users</para>
    
    <section>
        <title>How to Manage Tomcat   </title>
        <para>It's possible to manage Tomcat using eclipse-jmx</para>
        <para>  Currently, eclipse-jmx is able to connect to Tomcat without authentication or with password-based authentication.</para>
        <para> Using SSL for authentication is not supported: you need to make sure that the System property com.sun.management.jmxremote.ssl is set to false.
        </para>
        <para>  More information to manage Tomcat can be found in Tomcat management documentation </para>
        <para>  Instructions to manage remotely Tomcat are available in Tomcat's monitoring documentation.</para>
        
    </section>
    
    <section>
        <title>How to manage Eclipse Equinox</title>
        
        <para> You can manage Equinox through the Equinox monitoring framework.</para>  
        <para>  Once you have installed the Equinox monitoring framework and restarted Eclipse:</para>  
        <itemizedlist>
            <listitem><para>   Go to Window > Open Perspective > Other... and select the JMX Resource Management perspective</para></listitem>    
            <listitem><para>  Select JMX Server > Open Connection and click on OK</para></listitem> 
            <listitem><para>    Switch to the MBean explorer by going to Window > Show View > Other... and selecting the MBean Explorer</para></listitem>    
            <listitem><para>   click on the Connect... icon () in the MBean Explorer menu bar </para></listitem>   
            <listitem><para>   select the Advanced tab and set the JMX URL to  service:jmx:rmi:///jndi/rmi://:8118/jmxserver </para></listitem>   
        </itemizedlist>
        <para>  You now have access to the MBeans exposed by Equinox. </para>  
    </section>
    
    
   <section>
      <title>Managing JBoss Instances</title>
      <para>Managing JBoss instnaces is not supported with the JMX Tools alone. 
            You must also download and install the ASTools portion of the JBossTools distribution. 
            Even after installing the proper tooling, you cannot create a JBoss JMX connection yourself 
            or through the Connection Wizard. The first step is to create a JBoss Server. 
            The full instructions for this can be found in the AS Tools section, however, 
            the short summary is: </para>
      <itemizedlist>
          <listitem><para>Open the JBoss Servers View or the Servers View</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Right-click in the view and select New -> Server</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>In the "JBoss, a division of Red Hat" section, select a server version</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>If a runtime has not yet been created, you'll be prompted for the server's home directory, JDK, and configuration.</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Finish the wizard and note that you have a new entry in both the Server View and the MBean Explorer</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Start the server by right-clicking it and selecting Start</para></listitem>
          <listitem><para>Note that once the server is started, the JMX connection can be expanded</para></listitem>
       </itemizedlist>
       
       <para>Now you can explore MBeans exposed by a JBoss instance</para>
   </section> 
    
</chapter>
