<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<chapter id="intruduction"  xreflabel="introduction">
 <?dbhtml filename="introduction.html"?>
    
  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>This chapter covers the basics of working with JMX plugin, which is used to manage Java applications through JMX and its RMI Connector.</para>

  <para>To start using it, it's necessary to open JMX perspective. Go to Window > Open Perspective > Other... and then select JMX and click OK </para>
  
  <para>The JMX perspective is composed of a single view - MBean Explorer which lists the mbeans. When you double-click on a MBean in the MBean Explorer view, it opens a multi-page editor to manage the MBean.  The MBeanEditor is composed of 3 pages:</para>
  
 <orderedlist>
   <listitem><para> Attributes to get/set the attributes of the MBean</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para>Operations to invoke operations on the MBean</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para> Notifications to receive notifications from the MBean</para></listitem>
   <listitem><para> Info which displays general information about the MBean </para></listitem>
 </orderedlist>
  
<para>There is a button to update the MBean attribute value (if it is writable)</para>
    
  <section id="Connection">
      <title>Connection</title>
    <para> There are two ways to connect to an application with remote management enabled:</para>
    <para> The first step is the same for both - to connect to a MBean Server - click on the Connect... icon () in the MBean Explorer menu bar, 
    </para> 
    <para>Then to follow the simple one you just need to specify host, port (and optionally user name &amp; password) and click OK</para>
      <para>The default JMX URL is service:jmx:rmi:///jndi/rmi://localhost:3000/jmxrmi </para>
    
    <para> In case you need to connect to an application which has not used the "standard" JMX URL (e.g. Eclipse Equinox), you need chose more advance way, where it's necessary to  specify explicitly a JMX URL in the Advanced Tab of the JMX Connection window </para>
   
  
      <note><title>Note</title>
        <para>only JMX URL based on RMI are supported </para></note>
    </section>
  
  <section id="MBeanExporter">

    <title>MBean Explorer</title>
    <para>The MBean explorer displays the MBean features (both attributes and operations) in its hierarchy. Double-clicking on a feature will open a MBean Editor, display the page corresponding to the feature type and select the feature.</para>
    <para>Since It's possible to have many MBean Editors opened at the same time, the MBean Explorer has a Link With Editor checkbox to synchronize selections between the active MBean  Editor and the MBean explorer(and vice versa) </para>
    
    <!-- screens -http://code.google.com/p/eclipse-jmx/wiki/NewAndNoteworthy_0_1_2  -->
    <para>The MBean Explorer has also a filter text that can be used to filter among all the MBeans the few ones, which interest you.</para>
    
    <para>For example, if you are only interested by MBeans related to memory, typing memo will show only the MBeans registered under an ObjectName, which contains memo: </para>
    
    <para>A Collapse All button on the MBean Explorer toolbar is used to collapse all the MBeans and display only the domains. It is also possible to double click on a node to expand/collapse it. </para>
    
  </section>
  
  <section id="OpenMBeanAction">
    <title>Open MBean Action </title>
    <para>A Navigation action helps opening MBeans in a MBean Editor. This action is available either through the menu Navigate > Open MBean... or using the key shortcut Ctrl + Shift + M (&#8984;+ Shift + M on Mac OS X)</para>
  </section>
  
  
  </section>
  
</chapter>