<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<chapter id="intruduction" xreflabel="introduction">
  <?dbhtml filename="introduction.html"?>

  <title>Introduction</title>

  <para>This chapter covers the basics of working with JMX plugin, which is used to manage Java
  applications through JMX and its RMI Connector.</para>
  
  <section>
    <title> Requirements </title>
    <para> Requirements to use eclipse-jmx are the following: </para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para> eclipse-jmx is developed on Eclipse 3.3 milestones. It is also tested on latest
          stable 3.2 release.</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para> eclipse-jmx requires that Eclipse is run on a JDK 1.5.0 or above (due to dependencies
          on JMX packages which were introduced in Java 1.5.0)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Installation</title>
    
   <para>eclipse-jmx can be installed either by using Eclipse update manager or by downloading it and installing it manually in Eclipse.</para>
    
  <tip><title>Tip</title>
    <para>Check Requirements to see what is required to install and use eclipse-jmx. </para></tip>
    
 <section> <title>Manual Installation</title>
  <para> Follow the next steps to install the plugin manually: </para>
    
 <itemizedlist>  
   <listitem> <para>Download the latest release from http://code.google.com/p/eclipse-jmx/downloads/list</para></listitem>
<listitem> <para>   Unzip the file in you Eclipse installation</para></listitem>
    <listitem><para>(Re)Start Eclipse </para></listitem>
 </itemizedlist>   
 </section>
    
  <section> <title> Installation using Eclipes update manager</title>
    
    <para>In Eclipse:</para>
    
  <itemizedlist>  
    <listitem> <para>  go to Help > Software Updates > Find and Install...</para></listitem>
<listitem> <para> check Search for new features to install and click Next </para></listitem>
<listitem> <para>  click on New Remote Site...</para></listitem>
<listitem> <para>    in the New Update Site window, type:</para></listitem>
<listitem> <para>    Name: eclipse-jmx</para></listitem>
<listitem> <para>     URL: http://eclipse-jmx.googlecode.com/svn/trunk/net.jmesnil.jmx.update/ </para></listitem>
<listitem> <para>    click on OK</para></listitem>
<listitem> <para>     check eclipse-jmx and click on Finish</para></listitem>
<listitem> <para>     expand the features and select the latest one. Then click on Next </para></listitem>
<listitem> <para>     check I accept the terms in the license agreement and click on Next </para></listitem>
<listitem> <para>     click on Finish</para></listitem>
<listitem> <para>     once all the plug-ins are downloaded, click on Install All</para></listitem>
<listitem> <para>     finally, when ask to restart Eclipse, click on Yes</para></listitem>
  </itemizedlist>
  </section>  
    
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Quick Start</title>
 
  
  <para>To start using it, it's necessary to open JMX perspective. Go to Window > Open Perspective >
    Other... and then select JMX and click OK </para>

  <para>The JMX perspective is composed of a single view - MBean Explorer which lists the mbeans.
    When you double-click on a MBean in the MBean Explorer view, it opens a multi-page editor to
    manage the MBean. The MBeanEditor is composed of these pages:</para>

  <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
      <para> Attributes to get/set the attributes of the MBean</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para>Operations to invoke operations on the MBean</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para> Notifications to receive notifications from the MBean</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
      <para> Info which displays general information about the MBean </para>
    </listitem>
  </itemizedlist>

  <para>There is a button to update the MBean attribute value (if it is writable)</para>
  </section> 
  


<section>
  <title>How to Manage Tomcat   </title>
  <para>It's possible to manage Tomcat using eclipse-jmx</para>
    <para>  Currently, eclipse-jmx is able to connect to Tomcat without authentication or with password-based authentication.</para>
  <para> Using SSL for authentication is not supported: you need to make sure that the System property com.sun.management.jmxremote.ssl is set to false.
  </para>
  <para>  More information to manage Tomcat can be found in Tomcat management documentation </para>
  <para>  Instructions to manage remotely Tomcat are available in Tomcat's monitoring documentation.</para>
  
</section>
  
  <section>
    <title>How to manage Eclipse Equinox using eclipse-jmx</title>

  
<para> You can manage Equinox using eclipse-jmx through Equinox monitoring framework.</para>  
<para>  Once you have installed Equinox monitoring framework and restarted Eclipse:</para>  
<itemizedlist>
  <listitem><para>   Go to Window > Open Perspective > Other... and select the JMX Resource Management perspective</para></listitem>    
<listitem><para>  Select JMX Server > Open Connection and click on OK</para></listitem> 
  <listitem><para>    Switch to eclipse-jmx perspective by going to Window > Open Perspective > Other... and selecting the JMX perspective</para></listitem>    
  <listitem><para>   click on the Connect... icon () in the MBean Explorer menu bar </para></listitem>   
<listitem><para>   select the Advanced tab and set the JMX URL to  service:jmx:rmi:///jndi/rmi://:8118/jmxserver </para></listitem>   
</itemizedlist>
<para>  You now have access to the MBeans exposed by Equinox. </para>  
  </section>
  
  
   
  <section id="Connection">
    <title>Connection</title>
    <para> There are two ways to connect to an application with remote management enabled:</para>
    <para> The first step is the same for both - to connect to a MBean Server - click on the
      Connect... icon () in the MBean Explorer menu bar, </para>
    <para>Then to follow the simple one you just need to specify host, port (and optionally user
      name &amp; password) and click OK</para>
    <para>The default JMX URL is service:jmx:rmi:///jndi/rmi://localhost:3000/jmxrmi </para>

    <para> In case you need to connect to an application which has not used the "standard" JMX URL
      (e.g. Eclipse Equinox), you need chose more advance way, where it's necessary to specify
      explicitly a JMX URL in the Advanced Tab of the JMX Connection window </para>

    <note>
      <title>Note</title>
      <para>only JMX URL based on RMI are supported </para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section id="MBeanExporter">

    <title>MBean Explorer</title>
    <para>The MBean explorer displays the MBean features (both attributes and operations) in its
      hierarchy. Double-clicking on a feature will open a MBean Editor, display the page
      corresponding to the feature type and select the feature.</para>
    <para>Since It's possible to have many MBean Editors opened at the same time, the MBean Explorer
      has a Link With Editor checkbox to synchronize selections between the active MBean Editor and
      the MBean explorer(and vice versa) </para>

    <!-- screens -http://code.google.com/p/eclipse-jmx/wiki/NewAndNoteworthy_0_1_2  -->
    <para>The MBean Explorer has also a filter text that can be used to filter among all the MBeans
      the few ones, which interest you.</para>

    <para>For example, if you are only interested by MBeans related to memory, typing memo will show
      only the MBeans registered under an ObjectName, which contains memo: </para>

    <para>A Collapse All button on the MBean Explorer toolbar is used to collapse all the MBeans and
      display only the domains. It is also possible to double click on a node to expand/collapse it. </para>

  </section>

  <section id="OpenMBeanAction">
    <title>Open MBean Action </title>
    <para>A Navigation action helps opening MBeans in a MBean Editor. This action is available
      either through the menu Navigate > Open MBean... or using the key shortcut Ctrl + Shift + M
      (&#8984;+ Shift + M on Mac OS X)</para>
  </section>


</chapter>