<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<chapter id="modules">
	<title>Deploying Modules</title>

	<para>In this chapter it will be described how to deploy modules onto the server.</para>
	<para> First of all it is necessary to say that deploying to a server is mostly painless. There
		are several ways to do it provided by WTP, and some additional methods provided by JBoss
		Tools. These methods are discribed further in this chapter.</para>

	<section>
		<title>Deploying with Run On Server wizard</title>
		<para> The first WTP method is to right-click on a project, such as a Dynamic Web project,
			EJB project, or EAR project and then select <emphasis>
				<property>Run As &gt; Run on Server</property>
			</emphasis>. The resulting dialog allows you to select which supporting server the
			project can be published to. </para>
		<figure>
			<title>Define a New Server</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/modules/modules_1.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>Click <emphasis>
				<property>Next</property>
			</emphasis> button to see add or remove projects page where you can choose projects to
			configure them on server.</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Add or Remove Projects</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/modules/modules_2.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para> For the JBoss AS Server Adapters, publishing using this method will force a default,
			best-guess, packaging configuration for your project. This best-guess does not publish
			incrementally, but instead repackages your entire project into a .war, .jar, or .ear as
			appropriate, and then copies that file into the proper deploy directory. For quicker
			smarter deployment, you will need to create archives using the <link
				linkend="Project_archivesView">Project Archives view</link> and customize packaging
			yourself.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
		<title>Deploying with JBoss Server View</title>
		<para>As it has been already mentioned <emphasis>
				<property>JBoss Server View</property>
			</emphasis> contains two parts: the top part that displays all defined servers and the
			bottom part which provides categories with additional information. Thus, in this section
			we suggest two more ways to deploy resources onto the server.</para>
		<section>
			<title>Top part of JBoss Server View</title>
			<para>In the top part of the JBoss Servers View like in the Servers View you should right
				click on a server and select the <emphasis>
					<property>Add and Remove Projects</property>
				</emphasis> menu item. This will bring up a dialog allowing you to either publish
				projects or modules to a server, or remove them from the server.</para>
			<figure>
				<title>Add and Remove Projects</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/modules/modules_3.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>

			<para> If the selected module is a project like a Dynamic Web project, EJB project, or
				EAR project, it will be published as through <emphasis>
					<property>Run on Server</property>
				</emphasis> wizard, with a best-guess full package. If, however, the selected
				element is an archive from the <link linkend="Project_archivesView">Project Archives
					view</link>, it will be published according to the rules of that module
			type.</para>
		</section>
		<section>
			<title>Bottom part of JBoss Server View</title>
			<para>In the bottom part of <emphasis>
				<property>JBoss Server View</property>
			</emphasis> there is a category called <emphasis>
					<property>Modules</property>
				</emphasis> which should display all currently-published modules on the server.
				Right-clicking on the desired module and selecting <emphasis>
					<property>Full Publish</property>
				</emphasis> will force a full rebuild of the entire module.</para>
			<figure>
				<title>Full Publish</title>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/modules/modules_4.png"/>
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</figure>
		</section>
	</section>
	<section>
		<title>Deploying with Project Archives View</title>
		<para>In the Project Archives View you can right-click on any declared archive and select
			the <emphasis>
				<property>Publish To Server</property>
			</emphasis> element, as described in the <link linkend="Project_archivesView">Project
				Archives view</link> section of the Perspective chapter.</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Publish to Server</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/modules/modules_5.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para> The only way to ensure an <emphasis>
				<property>Incremental Build</property>
			</emphasis>, such as changes to one jsp, html, or .class file, is to enable the builder
			for that project. This is done by either changing the global preferences for the
				<property>Archives View</property>, or by enabling project-specific preferences and
			ensuring the builder is on.</para>
	</section>



</chapter>
