<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="perspective" xreflabel="perspective">
    <?dbhtml filename="perspective.html"?>
    <chapterinfo>
        <keywordset>
            <keyword>JBoss Developer Studio</keyword>
            <keyword>Eclipse</keyword>
            <keyword>Deploy</keyword>
            <keyword>Deployment</keyword>
            <keyword>JBoss</keyword>
        </keywordset>
    </chapterinfo>
    <title>JBoss AS Perspective</title>

    <para>This chapter tells how to manage installed JBoss Servers via <property>JBoss AS
            Perspective</property>.</para>

    <para>The <property>JBoss AS Perspective</property> is similar to the <property>Java
            Perspective</property>, but it contains a few additional views. Two of the additional
        views are standard views, specifically the <property>Console View</property> and the
            <property>Properties View</property>. The other two views that are added are the
            <property>Project Archives View</property> and the <property>JBoss Server
            View</property>.</para>

    <section id="JBossServerView">
        <?dbhtml filename="JBossServerView.html"?>
        <title>The JBoss Server View</title>
        <para>Let&apos;s have a look at the <property>JBoss Server View</property> and inspect
            in detail all parts it consists of. </para>

        <para>The <property>JBoss Server View</property> is based on the WTP view, Server View. The
            top part of the <property>JBoss Servers View</property> essentially embeds the original
            Server View directly into it, making slight changes to the context menu. A second part
            was added to provide additional information about the server selected in the top part. </para>

        <figure>
            <title>The JBoss Server View</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_1.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>


        <para>The view's toolbar provides quick access to starting a server (in debug mode, run
            mode, or profile mode), restarting a server, stopping a server, or publishing to a
            server.</para>
        <figure>
            <title>The JBoss Server View Toolbar</title>
            <mediaobject>
                <imageobject>
                    <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_19.png"/>
                </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
        </figure>

        <para>In order to debug your applications or EJB's that are deployed to the server, you must
            start the server in debug mode. By starting the server in debug mode, eclipse will allow
            you to set breakpoints on code in your workspace and step through the code.</para>

        <para><emphasis>
                <property>Start the server in profiling mode</property>
            </emphasis> button allows to enable profiling actions for your application. For more
            details on how to start using TPTP profiling with <property>JBoss Tools</property> refer
            to <link linkend="tptp_support">TPTP Support</link> chapter.</para>

        <para><emphasis>
                <property>Publish to the server</property>
            </emphasis> button on the extreme right will republish any modules where it has
            determined the workspace is out of sync with the server. It will attempt to do an
            incremental publish if it turns out that the module in question is capable of doing
            one.</para>

        <para>Now, let&apos;s get to know with both of the <property>JBoss Server
                View</property> parts.</para>

        <section role="updated">
            <title>Top Part of the JBoss Server View</title>
            <para>In the top part of the <property>JBoss Server View</property> all declared servers
                are represented as well as their current states, that is, whether they are started
                or stopped. </para>
            <figure>
                <title>Server Publish Status</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_18.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>The top part also shows the server&apos;s publish status. The fallowing table
                lists possible statuses.</para>

            <table>
                <title>Server Publish Status</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="3*"/>


                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry align="center">Status</entry>

                            <entry align="center">Description</entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>

                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry align="center">
                                <para>Republish</para>
                            </entry>

                            <entry align="center">
                                <para>The status which allows you to see if changes are
                                    awaiting</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry align="center">
                                <para>Publishing...</para>
                            </entry>

                            <entry align="center">
                                <para>The status which shows if changes are being updated</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                            <entry align="center">
                                <para>Synchronized</para>
                            </entry>

                            <entry align="center">
                                <para>The status which allows you to see if changes are
                                    in-sync</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>

            <para>By double-clicking on any server, an editor window will appear allowing you to
                edit parts of that server. On the figure you can see that a username/password is
                available in the UI when configuring the server. If you get an SecurityException
                when trying to launch the server, it is most likely because your server is protected
                and hence you need to fill the username/password fields with appropriate
                values.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Preferences Page for the Chosen Server</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_20.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>It should be pointed out that our server adapter by default tries to automatically
                detect the ports it needs for integrating with a <property>JBoss server</property>.
                Sometimes it can though be relevant to override this automatic detection if you are
                using some custom configuration. For this purposes the <emphasis>
                    <property>Server Ports</property>
                </emphasis> section in the <property>Server editor</property> is provided where the
                port settings are configurable. Click the <emphasis>
                    <property>Configure...</property>
                </emphasis> link to bring up the wizard for adjusting the settings for the
                Ports.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Server Ports Preferences</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_20_a.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>Press <emphasis>
                    <property>Edit XPath</property>
                </emphasis> button for the chosen Port to configure its XPath's values.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>XPath Pattern for a Server Port</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_20_b.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>The settings related to <emphasis>
                    <property>Publishing</property>
                </emphasis>, <emphasis>
                    <property>Timeouts</property>
                </emphasis> or <emphasis>
                    <property>Server Polling</property>
                </emphasis> can be also adjusted in the <property>Server editor</property>.</para>

            <para id="com_line_arg"><property>Server editor</property> makes it also possible to
                modify the server&apos;s launch configuration. It&apos;s just after clicking <emphasis>
                    <property>Open launch configuration</property>
                </emphasis> link. In the open window there are the tabs for setting command line
                arguments and other things that are relevant to launching the server.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Launch Configuration Properties</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_22.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>Look up <ulink
                    url="http://docs.jboss.org/jbossas/guides/installguide/r1/en/html/start-stop.html"
                    >here</ulink> to find parameters which can be specified for <property>JBoss
                    Server</property>.</para>

            <para>As the JBoss Servers have few properties to modify in this editor, a shortcut to
                the launch configuration has been provided in the context menu when right-clicking
                on a server.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Twiddle Server</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_21.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>The following table describes all these additional properties.</para>
            <table>
                <title>Server Properties through the Context Menu</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="3*"/>

                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry align="center">
                                <para>Name</para>
                            </entry>

                            <entry align="center">
                                <para>Description</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>

                    <tbody>
                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <para>New Server</para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>The option allows to define a new server</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Delete</para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Standard option that allows to delete the chosen server</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Start</para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>The action for stating a server in a run mode</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Debug</para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>The action for stating a server in a debug mode</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Stop</para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>The action for stopping a declared server</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Publish</para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>The action for synching the publish information between the
                                    server and workspace</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Clean</para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>The option for complete redeploying the resources</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Twiddle Server</para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>The option provides a dialog for running Twiddle commands
                                    against the Twiddle Server</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Edit Launch Configuration</para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>The option that provides an editor for editing launch
                                    configuration properties of the proper server</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Add and Remove Projects</para>
                            </entry>
                            <entry>
                                <para>The option allows to publish a new project to the server (if
                                    its type is supported)</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>

            <para>Mentioned above Twiddle is a JMX library that comes with JBoss, and you can use it
                to access any variables that exposed via the JBoss JMX interfaces.</para>
        </section>

        <section>
            <title>Bottom Part of the JBoss Server View</title>

            <para>Here, we dwell on the bottom part of the <property>JBoss Server
                View</property>.</para>
            <para>First, we should say that the bottom part is meant to provide additional
                functionality relevant to the server selected in the top part of the view. If a
                standard server element is selected from above, some of the extensions may still
                provide the additional information. Others may not. So, let&apos;s look at the
                currently available extensions to the bottom part of the <property>JBoss Server
                    View</property>.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>View Extensions</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_3.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>In order to access the view&apos;s preferences, you should access <emphasis>
                    <property>Window &gt; Preferences &gt; JBoss Tools &gt; JBoss
                        Servers &gt; View</property>
                </emphasis>. This preference page allows you to select which view extensions you
                want on or off, the order they appear in the view, as well as any other
                extension-specific preferences that may be available.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>View Preferences</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_2.png" scale="75"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>The first view extension is <emphasis>
                    <property>Modules</property>
                </emphasis> section. It shows which modules are currently deployed to the server,
                and allows you to remove them from the server, or force a full republish upon them.
                It only shows which modules have been deployed through Eclipse, not any and all
                modules that happen to be in the deploy directory.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Modules Action</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_4.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>The <emphasis>
                    <property>Event Log</property>
                </emphasis> will show relevant information to your server&apos;s startup,
                shutdown, and publish processes. This allows you to keep an eye on what&apos;s
                going on (such as automatic incremental deployment if you have it enabled). The only
                action available is to clear the <emphasis>
                    <property>Event Log</property>
                </emphasis>. However, if the <property>Properties View</property> is opened, you can
                receive further information on each <emphasis>
                    <property>Event Log</property>
                </emphasis> item (when available).</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Event Log Actions</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_5.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <figure>
                <title>Starting the Server</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_6.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>The <emphasis>
                    <property>XML Configuration</property>
                </emphasis> category allows you to quickly browse to descriptor files in your
                server's deploy directory and check or change the values. Its use requires the
                    <property>Properties view</property>. Basically, <emphasis>
                    <property>XML Configuration</property>
                </emphasis> includes XML XPaths where a xpath is a path used to access some specific
                part of an xml document. </para>

            <figure>
                <title>XML Configuration and Properties View</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_7.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <note>
                <title>Note:</title>
                <para>You are assumed to be familiar with XPath. If not, we highly suggested that
                    you look through an appropriate manual or tutorial on the topic.</para>
            </note>

            <para>The <emphasis>
                    <property>XML Configuration</property>
                </emphasis> category itself contains only a list of categories. <emphasis>
                    <property>Ports</property>
                </emphasis> are provided by default and is filled with many of the most commonly
                used ports in the <property>JBoss Server</property>. In the <property>Properties
                    view</property> you can see an identifier and nested files underneath in which
                that xpath can be found as well as its current value. The details of the xpath are
                hidden as all you need to see is only which file you&apos;re referring to and
                what its current value is.</para>

            <para> By right-clicking on <emphasis>
                    <property>XML Configuration</property>, </emphasis> you can create a new
                category. Besides, context menu for <emphasis>
                    <property>XML Configuration</property>
                </emphasis> category makes possible to disable it. You can disable any category in
                the bottom part of the <emphasis>
                    <property>JBoss Server View</property>.</emphasis> Look for them in the <emphasis>
                    <property>Inactive Categories</property>
                </emphasis> afterwards to re-enable.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Adding New Category</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_8.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>By right-clicking on <emphasis>
                    <property>Ports</property>
                </emphasis> or any other category in <emphasis>
                    <property>XML Configuration</property>
                </emphasis>, you can create a new xpath.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Adding New XPath</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_9.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>After that, the dialog shown below will appear.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Adding New XPath</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_10.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>The goal here is to get an end result where the XPath matches up with a necessary
                property. With that in mind, let&apos;s look how it works. If the property you
                want to reach is the value of the <emphasis>name</emphasis> attribute in the element
                    <emphasis>&lt;mbean&gt;</emphasis>, then your <emphasis>
                    <property>XPath Patten</property>
                </emphasis>should end with <emphasis>mbean</emphasis> and your <emphasis>
                    <property>Attribute Name</property>
                </emphasis> should be <emphasis>name</emphasis> like on the next figure.</para>

            <programlisting role="XML"><![CDATA[...
<server>
...
    <mbean code="org.jboss.ejb.EJBDeployer" 
                   name="jboss.ejb:service=EJBDeployer" xmbean-dd="">
  
     <!-- Inline XMBean Descriptor BEGIN -->
         <xmbean>
             <description>
                    The EJBDeployer responsible for ejb jar deployment</description> 
               ...
         </xmbean>
     </mbean>
</server>
]]></programlisting>

            <figure>
                <title>XPath Preview</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_23.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <tip>
                <title>Tip:</title>
                <para>Notice, when you type the fields autocomplete to help you locate exactly what
                    xpath you&apos;re looking for.</para>
            </tip>

            <para>Then, on the other hand, if your desired field is the text of an element
                    <emphasis>&lt;description&gt;</emphasis>, your <emphasis>
                    <property>XPath Patten</property>
                </emphasis> should end with <emphasis>description</emphasis> and <emphasis>
                    <property>Attribute Name</property>
                </emphasis> field should be left blank. When finished, click <emphasis>
                    <property>Preview</property>
                </emphasis> to see how many matches you have for that particular XPath.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>XPath Preview</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_24.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>As part of the <property>JBoss Server View</property> there is a <emphasis>
                    <property>JMX Console</property>
                </emphasis> section which allows you to browse and use the JMX exposed beans on the
                server.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>JMX Console</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_17.png" scale="75"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <section>
                <title>Relevant Resources Links</title>
                <para>Find more about XPath in the <ulink url="http://www.w3.org/TR/xpath20/">XPath
                        Documentation</ulink>.</para>
            </section>
        </section>

    </section>

    <section id="Project_archivesView">
        <title>Project Archives View</title>
        <para>Every application, whether Plain Old Java, J2EE, or some other language altogether,
            needs to be packaged in some way. In Java-related projects, many people use ANT. JBoss
            Tools comes with our own Archives tool with a bit easier and less-verbose XML and a
            handy user interface. The Project Archives plugin consists primarily of a view, that is
                <property>Project Archives View</property>, to set up each packaging
            configuration.</para>
        <para>So far, let&apos;s look through all functionality that the <property>Project
                Archives View</property> provides.</para>

        <section id="archives_overview">
            <title>Overview</title>

            <para>The packaging configuration for each project is stored in the project's root
                folder, and is in a file named <emphasis>
                    <property>.packages</property>
                </emphasis>, which has a fairly simple XML structure. Modifying the file by hand is
                neither required nor recommended, and using the UI is the official way of modifying
                your packaging structure.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Archives View</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_25.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>A project&apos;s configuration contains archives. On the image above there is
                only one archive, but a project can contain many. Inside the archive folders
                (testFolder), filesets, or other internal archives can be located. Internal archives
                and filesets may be directly inside of an archive, or in some sub-folder of that
                archive.</para>

            <para>In the upper right corner of the view you can see an icon which, when clicked,
                will build the selected top-level archive. Additionally, you can select <emphasis>
                    <property>Project &gt; Build Packages</property>
                </emphasis> when a project is selected in the <property>Packages View</property> to
                build all declared packages in that project&apos;s <emphasis>
                    <property>.packages</property>
                </emphasis> file. This will execute a full build on all declared archives.</para>
        </section>

        <section id="Creating_Archive">
            <title>Creating an Archive</title>
            <para>When creating a new archive, you have some different options at your disposal. If
                the project has no <emphasis>
                    <property>.packages</property>
                </emphasis> file, your options will be presented to you all at once to choose from.
                Otherwise you will right-click inside the view and select <emphasis>
                    <property>New Archive</property>
                </emphasis> to see your archive type options.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>Create an Archive</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_12.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <note>
                <title>Note:</title>
                <para>If you see only JAR from the list of available archive types, you should
                    verify whether AS Tools plugins/features are in place. EAR, EJB JAR and WAR
                    options are contributed by the AS Tools independently from webtools and the
                    virtual project model. Thus, without them only JAR will show up.</para>
            </note>

            <para><property>JAR</property> is the standard archive type, and does very little
                configuration, leaving most of the work up to you. You can customize the name, add
                folders, filesets, and inner jars to it.</para>
            <para>The other types, for the most part, simply start off with a default setting,
                usually the jar with some specific children based on an expected structure of the
                project. For example, if the project is a Dynamic Web Project, and you create a
                    <property>WAR</property> archive, the archive will be created with a few
                filesets relevant to the known structure of the project.</para>

            <para>Here is the first page of all New archive wizards. It is the same for any archive
                type and the only page in the <property>New Jar Wizard</property>.</para>
            <figure>
                <title>New JAR Wizard</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_13.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>

            <para>The page is pretty simple. All it asks for is the name of your new archive, a
                destination, which we'll get to in a moment, and whether the archive is exploded or
                packaged up.</para>
            <para>The destination of an archive can be anywhere on the filesystem, anywhere in the
                workspace, inside some other archive, or inside a folder declared inside an archive.
                You can browse to workspace or filesystem destinations by clicking on their
                respective buttons. To select a destination inside some other archive, you'll need
                to press the <emphasis>
                    <property>Workspace...</property>
                </emphasis> button. At the bottom of the list, you&apos;ll see archives that
                have been declared in the workspace.</para>
            <section id="CreatingaFolder">
                <title>Creating a Folder</title>
                <para>Creating a folder is much easier. You simply right-click on an archive or
                    folder you want your new folder to be a child under. The only piece of required
                    information is naming the file.</para>
            </section>
            <section id="CreatingaFileSet">
                <title>Creating a FileSet</title>
                <para>To create a new fileset, you click on an available target location such as an
                    archive, a nested archive, or a folder within an archive, and select <emphasis>
                        <property>New Fileset</property>
                    </emphasis>.</para>
                <para>The <property>New Fileset Wizard</property> requires a destination (where the
                    files will go), and a root directory (or where the files are coming from). The
                    source can be anywhere in the workspace or from the filesystem at large.</para>

                <figure>
                    <title>Adding a New FileSet</title>
                    <mediaobject>
                        <imageobject>
                            <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_26.png"/>
                        </imageobject>
                    </mediaobject>
                </figure>

                <para>Below that, the fileset requires only an includes pattern and an excludes
                    pattern. As you type in either of these fields, the preview viewer should update
                    itself with which files are matched.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
        <section id="View_Actions">
            <title>Archive Actions</title>
            <figure>
                <title>Context Menu on the Item</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_14.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>The context menu on the items in the view is extendable, but there are several
                that come standard.</para>

            <table>
                <title>Context Menu on the Item</title>
                <tgroup cols="2">
                    <colspec colnum="1" align="left" colwidth="1*"/>
                    <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="3*"/>


                    <thead>
                        <row>
                            <entry align="center">
                                <para>Name</para>
                            </entry>

                            <entry align="center">
                                <para>Description</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>
                    </thead>

                    <tbody>

                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Build Archive (Full)</para>
                            </entry>

                            <entry>
                                <para>The action enabled only on top-level archives, which initiates
                                    a full build on that archive</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Edit Archive</para>
                            </entry>

                            <entry>
                                <para>Standard action that brings up the wizard associated with that
                                    particular node type and allows the details to be changed</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Delete Archive</para>
                            </entry>

                            <entry>
                                <para>Deleting node is standard action with deletion not needing an
                                    explanation</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>

                        <row>
                            <entry>
                                <para>Publish To Server</para>
                            </entry>

                            <entry>
                                <para>The action means the ability to publish to a declared
                                    server</para>
                            </entry>
                        </row>

                    </tbody>
                </tgroup>
            </table>
        </section>

        <section id="PublishToServer">
            <title>Publishing to Server</title>
            <para>Finally, you&apos;ll need to publish your application to a server. Here, we
                show you how to do it with the help of <emphasis>
                    <property>Archives View</property>
                </emphasis>.</para>

            <figure>
                <title>Context Menu on the Item</title>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata fileref="images/perspective/perspective_15.png"/>
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </figure>
            <para>The dialog above appears after selecting <emphasis>
                    <property>Publish To Server</property>
                </emphasis>. To simply publish once, you just select the server(s) that you want,
                and finish. If you want the <emphasis>
                    <property>Publish to Server</property>
                </emphasis> action on that particular Archive to publish always to that set of
                servers, then check the appropriate checkbox. And finally, to enable automatic
                publishing upon build events, check the last checkbox.</para>
            <para>The automatic publishing feature is nice if, for example, your package's
                destination (where it is built) is a temporary folder and you want the archive
                published to several servers. If you only really want your archive published to one
                server, it might be easier to have the archive's destination folder be the deploy
                folder of the server.</para>
        </section>
        <section>
            <title>Relevant Resources Links</title>
            <para>Refer to <ulink url="http://ant.apache.org/manual/index.html">Ant manual</ulink>
                to find more on how to build your applications with help of Ant.</para>

            <para>At this point, you are guessed to be familiar with <property>JBoss AS
                    Perspective</property> and your next step now is to explore how to work with
                different kinds of projects.</para>
        </section>

    </section>


</chapter>
