<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<chapter id="webtools">
	<title>Projects</title>
	<para>The most popular of the projects we deal with are the J2EE ones, such as Dynamic Web
		Project, EJB Project, or EAR project. Web projects of <property>JBoss Tools</property> are
		Struts, JSF and Seam projects. All of them are called faceted projects. Thus, in this
		chapter we are going to tell you about facets the main benefit of which to provide proper
		structuring and packaging for any type of project.</para>

	<section>
		<title>Faceted Projects Overview</title>
		<para>The idea behind faceted projects is that each project can accept units of
			functionality, or facets, which can be added or removed by the user. Most often, these
			facets either add to the project's classpath, enable a builder, or watch the project in
			some other fashion. Generally, every project concerned has at least one facet when
			it&apos;s created. As an example, a Web project has a WebDoclet facet, or an EJB
			Project has an EJB Module facet as prerequisites.</para>

		<para> WTP projects have undergone some criticism as being
			<emphasis>over-engineered</emphasis> or too restrictive in their design. WTP projects
			are set up in a tree-relationship to each other, where one project can be a child of
			another. For example, an EAR project may have a Web Project child, an EJB project child,
			or other types.</para>

		<para> However, the benefit of this is that the structure of your projects is then known,
			and packaging it up *should* be trivial. Apparently, if your project is non-standard, or
			you feel too confined by such rigid structural requirements, you can still choose to
			package your project using the <link linkend="Project_archivesView">Archives
			plugin</link>.</para>
	</section>


	<section>
		<title>Adding Facets to a Project</title>

		<para>In this section we&apos;re going to consider the facets added by <property>JBoss
				Tools</property> and show how you can configure them in a project: add new ones or
			modify already existing configuration of the facets.</para>

		<para>One way to configure the facets is doing it while organizing a new project. To
			demonstrate this let&apos;s create a new <property>Dynamic Web Project</property> by
			selecting <emphasis>
				<property>File &gt; New &gt; Other...</property>
			</emphasis> and then <emphasis>
				<property>Web &gt; Dynamic Web Project</property>. </emphasis></para>
		<figure>
			<title>New Dynamic Web Project</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/webtools/webtools_1.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>Click <emphasis>
				<property>Next</property>
			</emphasis> and you will see Dynamic Web Project page like on the figure below.</para>

		<para> The first page of most WTP projects allows you to target a specific runtime,
			representing a server's library location. It will also provide you the ability to add
			this project to an EAR project, and select a preselected default set of facets, called
			a configuration, rather than manually select each facet you might want.</para>
		<para> Selecting the runtime, again, allows the project to install the proper classpaths to
			the project so it knows what code to compile against.</para>

		<figure id="dyn_web_project">
			<title>New Dynamic Web Project</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/webtools/webtools_2.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>Click on the <emphasis>
				<property>Modify</property>
			</emphasis> button next to <property>Configuration</property> section in order to open
			the wizard which allows you to modify a chosen configuration. The wizard looks as
			follows.</para>

		<figure id="project_facets">
			<title>Project Facets Wizard</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/webtools/webtools_3.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>

		<para>Here part of the listed facets are those which are provided by WTP. Some of them are
			added by <property>JBoss Tools</property>. They are:</para>
		<itemizedlist>
			<listitem>
				<para>BIRT Charting Runtime Component</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>BIRT Reporting Runtime Component</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>JBoss ESB</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>JBoss Portlets</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>JBoss Web Services</para>
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
				<para>Seam</para>
			</listitem>
		</itemizedlist>

		<para>On this wizard page you can enable or disable any facet as well as change it version.
			What you should note here is that some facets or facets versions may conflict with each
			other. In case of incompatibility you&apos;ll be prompted about this in the combo
			box underneath.</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Facet Constraints</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/webtools/webtools_4.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>When switching on the <emphasis>
				<property>Runtimes</property>
			</emphasis> tab on the right you&apos;ll see the current server Runtime.</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Runtimes on the Project Facets Wizard</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/webtools/webtools_5.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>On this tab you can also create a new Server Runtime and make it primary by pressing <emphasis>
				<property>Make Primary</property>
			</emphasis> button after enabling it.</para>

		<para>Clicking on <emphasis>
				<property>OK</property>
			</emphasis> will save the chosen configuration of the facets and return you to the <link
				linkend="dyn_web_project">Dynamic Web Project wizard</link>. Further pages in the
			wizard are specific to either the project type or the facets selected.</para>


		<para>If you need to configure the facets for the existing project, you should bring up the
			context menu for selected project and click <emphasis>
				<property>Properties</property>
			</emphasis> and then <emphasis>
				<property>Project Facets</property>. </emphasis> This will bring up the familiar
				<link linkend="project_facets">Project Facets wizard</link>, where you can create
			your own custom facets configuration.</para>

		<para/>

	</section>
	<section id="rel_resources_links">
		<title>Relevant Resources Links</title>

		<para>More on the WTP facets you can read in the <ulink
				url="http://help.eclipse.org/ganymede/index.jsp?topic=/org.eclipse.jst.j2ee.doc.user/topics/cfacets.html"
				>eclipse help</ulink>.</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
