<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<chapter id="webtools">
	<title>Projects</title>
	<para>The most popular of the projects we deal with are the J2EE ones, such as Dynamic Web
		Project, EJB Project, or EAR project. Web projects of JBoss Tools are Struts, JSF and Seam
		projects. All of them are called faceted projects. Thus, in this chapter we are going to
		tell you about facets the main benefit of which to provide proper structuring and packaging
		for any type of project.</para>

	<section>
		<title>Faceted Projects Overview</title>
		<para>The idea behind faceted projects is that each project can accept units of
			functionality, or facets, which can be added or removed by the user. Most often, these
			facets either add to the project's classpath, enable a builder, or watch the project in
			some other fashion. Generally, every project concerned has at least one facet when
			it&apos;s created. As an example, a Web project has a WebDoclet facet, or an EJB
			Project has an EJB Module facet as prerequisites.</para>

		<para> WTP projects have undergone some criticism as being
			<emphasis>over-engineered</emphasis> or too restrictive in their design. WTP projects
			are set up in a tree-relationship to each other, where one project can be a child of
			another. For example, an EAR project may have a Web Project child, an EJB project child,
			or other types.</para>

		<para> However, the benefit of this is that the structure of your projects is then known,
			and packaging it up *should* be trivial. Apparently, if your project is non-standard, or
			you feel too confined by such rigid structural requirements, you can still choose to
			package your project using the <link linkend="Project_archivesView">Archives
			plugin</link>.</para>
	</section>


	<section> <!-- mark as updated -->
		<title>Adding Facets to a Project</title>

		<para>There are two ways to add facets to a project. The first way is to include facets into
			already existing project. For that you should bring up the context menu for selected
			project and click <emphasis>
				<property>Properties</property>.
			</emphasis> At this point, choose <emphasis>
				<property>Project Facets</property>
			</emphasis> from the left. It will represent a list of the facets for your project and
			give opportunity to modify it by clicking on <emphasis>
				<property>Modify Project...</property>
			</emphasis> button.</para>

		<figure>
			<title>Adding Facets to the Existing Project</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/webtools/webtools_0.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>

		<para> The other way is adding necessary facets while organizing a new project. To
			demonstrate it let&apos;s create a new <property>Dynamic Web Project</property>
			selecting as usual <emphasis>
				<property>File &gt; New &gt; Other...</property>
			</emphasis> and then <emphasis>
				<property>Web &gt; Dynamic Web Project</property>.
			</emphasis></para>
		<figure>
			<title>New Dynamic Web Project</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/webtools/webtools_1.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para>Click <emphasis>
				<property>Next</property>
			</emphasis> and you will see Dynamic Web Project page.</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Faceted Project Wizard: First Page</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/webtools/webtools_2.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para> The first page of most WTP projects allows you to target a specific runtime,
			representing a server's library location. It will also provide you the ability to add
			this project to an EAR project, and select a pre-selected default set of facets, called
			a configuration, rather than manually select each facet you might want.</para>
		<para> Selecting the runtime, again, allows the project to install the proper classpaths to
			the project so it knows what code to compile against.</para>
		<figure>
			<title>Faceted Project Wizard: Second Page</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/webtools/webtools_3.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para> The second page of the wizard allows you to enable or disable specific facets, as
			described above. Some facets may require others, and some may conflict with others, but
			on the whole this page allows you to add any number of facets that don&apos;t
			conflict with each other. It means that the list doesn&apos;t show those facets that
			couldn&apos;t be in the same project. To view the information on limitations and
			requirements for the chosen facet right-click on the facet and press <emphasis>
				<property>Show Constraints</property>.</emphasis></para>

		<figure>
			<title>Facet Constraints</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/webtools/webtools_4.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>

		<para>Notice that here it is also possible to change the version of any facet. If
			the chosen version isn&apos;t compatible with any other facet version, you&apos;ll be prompted
			about this in the combo box underneath.</para>
		
		<figure>
			<title>Facet Constraints</title>
			<mediaobject>
				<imageobject>
					<imagedata fileref="images/webtools/webtools_5.png"/>
				</imageobject>
			</mediaobject>
		</figure>
		<para> Further pages in the wizard are specific to either the project type, or the facets
			selected.</para>

	</section>
</chapter>
