<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<chapter id="webtoolsProjects">
  <title>Webtools Projects (out of date!)</title>
  <section><title>Description</title>
  <para>
	  Webtools provides what are called "faceted" projects, 
	  Their most popular such projects are their J2EE projects,
	  such as their Dynamic Web Project, their EJB Project, 
	  or their EAR project. </para>
  <para>
	  The idea behind faceted projects is that each project 
	  can accept units of functionality, or facets, which can be 
	  added or removed by the user. Some examples of these facets
	  are adding a webdoclet facet to a web project, or an 
	  ejbdoclet to an EJB Project. </para>
  <para>
	  Most often, these "facets" either add to the project's classpath, 
	  enable a builder, or watch the project in some other fashion. </para>
  <para>
	  WTP projects have undergone some criticism as being 
	  <emphasis>over-engineered</emphasis> or too restrictive in their
	  design. WTP projects are set up in a tree-relationship to each other,
	  where one project can be a child of another. For example, an EAR
	  project may have a Web Project child, an EJB project child, 
	  or other types. </para>
  <para>
	  The benefit of this is that the structure of your projects is
	  then known, and packaging it up *should* be trivial. However,
	  if your project is non-standard, or you feel too confined by
	  such rigid structural requirements, you can still choose to 
	  package your project using the Archives plugin as described
	  in the last chapter</para>

  </section>
  <section><title>Faceted Project Wizards</title>
    <figure id="faceted1"> <title>Faceted Project Wizard: First Page</title>
    <mediaobject>
	<alt>Faceted Project Wizard: First Page</alt>
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata width="5in" scalefit="0" 
			fileref="..\..\..\..\reference\en\images\projects\wizard1.jpg"/>
	</imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
	   The first page of most WTP projects allows you to target a specific runtime,
	   representing a server's library location. It will also provide you the ability to 
	   add this project to an EAR project, and select a pre-selected default set of facets,
	   called a configuration, rather than manually select each facet you might want.</para>
   <para>
	   Selecting the runtime, again, allows the project to install the proper
	   classpaths to the project so it knows what code to compile against.</para>
    <figure id="faceted2"> <title>Faceted Project Wizard: Second Page</title>
    <mediaobject>
	<alt>Faceted Project Wizard: Second Page</alt>
	<imageobject>
		<imagedata width="5in" scalefit="0" 
			fileref="..\..\..\..\reference\en\images\projects\wizard2.jpg"/>
	</imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
   </figure>
   <para>
	   The second page of the wizard allows you to enable or disable specific facets, as
	   described above. Some facets may require others, and some may conflict with others, 
	   but on the whole this page allows you to add any number of facets that don't conflict
	   with each other. </para>
   <para>
	   Further pages are specific to either hte project type, or the facets selected.</para>
   </section>
</chapter>	
