<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<chapter id="intruduction" xreflabel="introduction">
  <?dbhtml filename="introduction.html"?>

  <title>Introduction</title>
  <para><property>JBoss Tools</property>&apos; JMX project is a fork of <ulink
    url="http://code.google.com/p/eclipse-jmx/">eclipse-jmx</ulink>, a project by Jeff Mesnil.
    It was forked with permission. </para>
  <section>
    <title>What is JMX Tools?</title>
   <para><property>JMX Tools</property> allows to setup multiple JMX connections and provides view
    for exploring the JMX tree and execute operations directly from Eclipse.</para>

  <para>This chapter covers the basics of working with <property>JMX plugin</property>, which is
    used to manage Java applications through JMX and its RMI Connector.</para>

  <figure>
    <title>JMX Tools</title>
    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata fileref="images/eclipse-jmx_0.2.png"/>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  </section>

  <section><title>Key Features of JMX Tools</title>
    <para>For a start, we propose you to look through the table of main features of JMX Tools:</para>
    <table>
      
      <title>Key Functionality for JMX Tools</title>
      <tgroup cols="3">
        
        <colspec colnum="1" align="left" colwidth="2*"/>
        <colspec colnum="2" colwidth="4*"/>
        <colspec colnum="3" align="left" colwidth="2*"/>
        
        <thead>
          <row>
            <entry>Feature</entry>
            <entry>Benefit</entry>
            <entry>Chapter</entry>
          </row>
        </thead>
        
        <tbody>
          
          <row>
            <entry><para>MBean Explorer</para></entry>
            <entry><para>MBean Explorer is a useful view with a text filter that displays domains, mbeans, attributes, and operations inside a connection.</para></entry>
            <entry>
              <link linkend="mbean_explorer">MBean Explorer</link>
            </entry>
          </row>
          
          <row>
            <entry><para>MBean Editor</para></entry>
            <entry><para>MBean Editor is a multi-page editor to manage MBeans.</para></entry>
            <entry>
              <link linkend="mbean_editor">MBean Editor</link>
            </entry>
          </row>
       </tbody>
      </tgroup>
    </table>
  </section>
  
  <section>
    <title>Requirements and Installation</title>
  <section>
    <title> Requirements</title>
    <para>Requirements to use <property>JMX Tools</property> are the following:</para>
    
    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><property>JMX Tools</property> is developed on Eclipse 3.4.x milestones</para>
      </listitem>
      <listitem>
        <para><property>JMX Tools</property> requires that Eclipse is run on a JDK 1.5.0 or above
          (due to dependencies on JMX packages which were introduced in Java 1.5.0)</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
    <title>Installation</title>
    <para>Here, we are going to explain how to install the <property>JMX plugin</property> into
      Eclipse.</para>

    <para><property>JMX Tools</property> is one module of the <property>JBoss Tools</property>
      project. <property>JMX Tools</property> has no dependency on any other part of <property>JBoss
        Tools</property>, and can be downloaded standalone. Even though the <property>JMX
        Tools</property> have no dependencies, other plugins, such as <property>AS Tools</property>,
      do depend on the JMX Tooling and even extend it. </para>

    <para>You can find the <property>JBoss Tools</property> plugins over at the <ulink
        url="http://labs.jboss.com/tools/download.html">download pages</ulink>. The only
      package you&apos;ll need to get is the JMX Tooling, however the <property>AS
        Tools</property> would give you a more full experience when using JMX with JBoss Servers.
      You can find further download and installation instructions on the JBoss Wiki in the <ulink
        url="http://labs.jboss.com/wiki/InstallingJBossTools">InstallingJBossTools</ulink>
      section.</para>
  </section>
 </section>
</chapter>
