<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<chapter id="mbean_explorer"  xreflabel="mbean_explorer">
    <?dbhtml filename="mbean_explorer.html"?>
    
    <title>MBean Explorer</title>
    <para>The <property>MBean Explorer</property> displays the MBean features (both attributes and operations) in its
        hierarchy. Double-clicking on a feature will open a <property>MBean Editor</property>, display the page
        corresponding to the feature type and select the feature.</para>
    
    <figure>
        <title>MBean Explorer Features</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/mbean-explorer-features.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>
    
    <para>Since it&apos;s possible to have many MBean Editors opened at the same time, the <property>MBean Explorer</property>
        has the Link With Editor button 
        
        <inlinemediaobject>   
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/link-with-editor_0.2.0.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
        
        to synchronize selections between the active <property>MBean Editor</property> and
        the <property>MBean Explorer</property> (and vice versa).</para>
    
    <para>The <property>MBean Explorer</property> has also a filter text that can be used to filter among all the MBeans
        the few ones, which interest you.</para>
    
    <para>For example, if you are only interested by MBeans related to memory, typing memo will show
        any node (domain, mbean, attribute, or operation) that matches that text, as well as 
        that node&apos;s parents and children. So if an MBean matches, all attributes and operations from 
        that bean will show.  If, however, an attribute or operation name (a leaf node) matches, 
        only that node and its parents in the tree will show.</para>

    <figure>
        <title>Query Filter</title>
        <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/mbean-explorer-query.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
    </figure>

    
    <para>The <emphasis>
        <property>Collapse All</property></emphasis> button 
        
        <inlinemediaobject>   
            <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/collaps_all.png"/>
            </imageobject>
        </inlinemediaobject>
        
        on the <property>MBean Explorer</property> toolbar is used to collapse all the MBeans and
        display only the domains. It is also possible to double click on a node to expand/collapse it. </para>
    
</chapter>
